Instructor: Again, now to follow most
of the lecture in this section,
we will need the Vagrant VM
that we created in the previous section.
Most of the lecture follows on centOS
but then we have openSUSE also.
Run the command vagrant global -status,
to check the VM status
and where they are located.
Right, so we we're going to get into this folder
so cd /f/vagrant-vm/centos/
switch to the folder that shows, over there,
where you created the VM, right?
Let's clear the screen
and we'll do vagrant up to bring up this VM.
Okay, it's going to take a moment.
It's the same VM.
The VM was already created for me
so it is just powering on now.
I don't know if that's even a correct grammar,
powering on, so it's just coming up.
Okay, it's up in less than a minute.
vagrant ssh, to log into it.
Okay, I'm in the VM
and I'm going to issue the command clear.
Okay, now, four very basic commands.
First, whoami,
see what user you are.
Say, it's vagrant user.
pwd, present working directory,
it will show you where you are.
So, vagrant user is in vagrant's home directory
/home/vagrant.
ls command to see
what is there in the current directory,
there's nothing.
cat command to read a file
and we will mention this file path /etc/os-release,
this file shows what is the operating system
and what version it is.
Okay, now look at the prompt.
This is the user, we checked it.
whoami command, vagrant user, at the rate,
hostname, so there's no hostname set,
so by default will be localhost,
tilda symbol that represents
that you are in the home directory.
Home directory of what?
Of vagrant user.
So, we did pwd.
You see, we are in the home directory
of vagrant user /home/vagrant,
and then a dollar that represents
its a normal user shell.
Now, watch, I'm going to run this command, sudo-i.
This command will switch
to root user from vagrant user
and only vagrant user has permission
to switch to root user,
so vagrant user can, anytime, run sudo -i
and switch to root user.
Now, look at the prompt.
Once again, it has changed.
Username, root hostname
and tilda means the home directory of root user.
And hash means this is the root user's shell.
Now, check once again, whoami?
root user,
pwd, /root.
Now, /root is the home directory
of the root user, right?
Observe there is a slash
at the beginning and then slash root.
Let's do cd /,
this means go to the root directory.
I don't want you to confuse here,
/, just a / at the beginning
or only the / means the root directory,
which is different from the root users home directory.
Watch this, cd /, pwd,
I'm in the root directory,
not in root user's home directory.
I'm in the root directory.
Do ls and you should see all the files
that is present in the root directory.
Or you can say,
these are all the files in this operating system.
Observe there is /, there is a home, right?
That's why this /home, right?
And there should be root there,
root, right?
That's why it's /root.
So, we are in the root directory now.
Once again, this is root directory.
This is root users home directory.
If it's still confusing, don't worry,
we will get into this in detail later.
For now, I want you to become comfortable
with the commands, with the basic commands.
Now, if you type cd and hit Enter,
then you'll come back
to the home directory of the user.
You see that, it changed to tilda
if you do pwd, see /root.
So, whenever you're lost,
you can do cd and hit Enter.
You come back to the user's home directory, right?
Also, check what user you are, right?
So, you come back to that user's home directory.
Now, I am clearing the screen.
Now, let's understand the directory structure
cd /,
this is called as the root directory.
Forward slash is the root directory.
And if you do ls here,
you will see all the directories
or files that you have
in this Linux operating system.
This is the top level directory
of Linux operating system
or any Nix operating system.
So, you should see here,
a root that is the root
user's home directory.
You should see a home directory
inside that you'll have users' home directories.
You see etc for configuration boot directory
where you have bootloader and kernel.
You see media /mnt for mound points,
/opt, it's an optional directory
and we'll be using that later.
So, home directory /root for root user
normal user /home/username.
User executable is in /bin.
There's bin directory.
So, we are already here in the root directory.
We can just do cd bin.
If you are somewhere else,
you can do cd /bin.
Okay, you're giving the absolute path.
This is called as absolute path.
Absolute path always begins with the root directory.
And /bin, if you do ls,
you should see a lot of files.
These are mostly the user executable programs
like mv, is to move files,
scp to copy files to remote Linux machines,
yum, and you'll see many more.
You'll see all your commands
that you're using as a normal user here.
Like whoami,
pwd.
So, these are user executable programs.
If you go to /usr,
sorry /sbin,
these are the programs
that are executable by root user
like for example, mkfs.ext4,
this is for formatting partition,
which cannot be done by the normal user,
reboot command, to reboot your operating system.
This can be executed by normal user also,
provided you give sudo
and many other system executable commands.
So user executable, system executable.
Let's see the configuration directory.
/etc and you should see here the configuration files
and directories, like hostname.
If you wanna change the hostname,
you can see this file.
You can give the complete cat /etc/hostname/
and you should see the current hostname.
If you want, you can edit this file and change it.
We'll be learning that,
how to edit files through vi editor.
Yum configuration
which is the package manager in Red Hat machine.
Like you have Google Play Store
on your Android phone, like that.
Networks configuration and so many other
configuration files.
We'll be seeing a lot of files from this directory.
Temporary files, /tmp.
We'll be using these directories also,
especially when we write scripts
and you want to put some temporary data,
we'll put it in /tmp directory.
And most of the automation tool
is so many tools when they're doing some operation,
they need some files for temporary purpose,
they'll use /tmp directory.
Do not store anything over here,
which you want to use later.
This is just for temporary purpose.
/boot kernels and bootloaders.
cd /boot.
So, that's your bootloader, initramfs,
vmlinuz, that's your your kernel.
And there's a grub directory inside this
where you'll have the configuration for booting,
grub2, this you get it more into system administration.
You need to change the booting parameters
the kernel version, stuff like that.
Then, you can use these configurations.
/var, or /srv to store the server data.
We'll be seeing that later.
System information, /proc /sys.
Let me show you one example from this.
If you are anywhere in the Linux system
and if you want to come back
to your home directory,
you can just say cd and hit Enter.
You'll come back to your home directory.
From here, let's go to /proc
and you will see some files over here.
These are dynamic files.
Mostly, they'll be changing
based on the system information.
Like for example, there is a command called uptime
which will read how long the system is up and running.
So, the system is up from past 13 minutes.
It'll show you how many users are logged in
and the current load average.
We'll understand load average later.
But what I want to point you here
is this is a command that reads information
from this file.
You should see uptime file here
that you'll have some information,
/proc/uptime but it may not be user readable.
Or you have command like free -m
which shows you the RAM size.
And these things are dynamic.
These things changes
and that's why content in this directory
will be regularly changing.