OK, currently I am a root user.
If I say exit.
I will be logged out from root user and I'll go back to my current user, if I hit exit once again,
I will be exiting or logging out from vagrant user.
So I will come back to my windows machine, vagrant ssh, login again.
So as you can see now, I am logged in as vagrant user to my machine, I can do sudo -i and
I can switch to root user again.
I could exit.
I go back to vagrant user.
OK, now some very basic file based commands.
I'm in my vagrant users home dir and I'm going to create some directories over here, so I will create a dir named
dev and I will create multiple directories.
One is ops and one as backup directories.
So I have now total three degrees.
In my home dir.
I'm going to use now touch command, touch is a command that will create empty files or it will update files
timestamp.
So I see touch and I will say testfile.txt
The extension is not so important here now, but anyways of will give it.
So touch, command, creates empty file, there is nothing in that file, we can create multiple files also
like that.
I will give name as devopsfile and I'll use curly braces and I will give a range of numbers.
1..10
And I'll put an extension also, .txt
hit enter and now you should see 10 files that start with name devops then the number of the file
and then ends with .txt
So it does something like multiplication gives you range one to 10.
OK, now let's see, copying files will copy a file, cp devopsfile1.txt
to dev dir
I say dev and give /
This is the source, and that is the destination, hit enter.
And if I do, ls dev
I can see the file is copied there now, I have given the relative part, I am already here.
I have dev dir so I can say ls dev/
But let's say, I'm in tmp dir
And if I want to list dev dir, which is not here, so I'm going to say list and I'll give absolute
absolute path. /home/vagrant/dev
So both give me the same result.
This was a relative path and this is absolute path.
Now, going back to my home dir, cd, enter
I clear the screen now.
And back to my home directory.
So that was copying a file.
I will show you now how to copy the file with absolute path source and destination board.
So let's again go to /tmp dir or any other dir you want.
I want to copy devopsfile to /tmp dir again.
So I will say cp, absolute path. /home/vagrant/devopsfile2.txt and /home/vagrant/dev
/home/vagrant/dev/
OK, I've given sources the absolute path and destination as an absolute path.
So as long as you don't become comfortable with Linux filesystem, use absolute path, it's a good practice,
even if you're located the same place, if you're in home dir, still use the absolute path for
few days.
So you become comfortable with Linux filesystem structure.
OK, there's also one more way to go back to home dir,  cd and using ~ symbol.
This should be just below your escape button, it does the same thing tilde ~ means home dir.
So vagrant users home directory and back.
OK, now let's copy a dir into another directories, so I will copy dev dir, I'm giving the
relative path to backup directory again relative path, so I say a backupdir/.
So this directly will be copied inside this directly or does it.
Let's see.
OK, we got some response back, it's an error, actually, ommiting dir, if you do a list to
back dir, there is nothing. Try absolute path also for practice
Nothing.
So that did not work out.
That's because you cannot copy directories.
If you want to copy dir, you have to use an option called -r
And I will say copy dir to back up dir..
And that worked, you can do ls backup dir or try with absolute path again, use up Arrow.
I'm showing again and again absolute path so you can become comfortable, that's all, if you're already
comfortable, use whatever you want.
relative path or absolute path
OK, now that brings me to the Linux syntax, Linux command syntax, so you have
command options and then the arguments.
So that is the command we use.
Right?
So the syntax is like this.
First, you have the command, which is cp in this case, and then you have options, you have many
options.
We'll see how we can find other options also.
And then you have arguments.
Now, some places you can just use the command like ls, just the command, but there are options also
with this command.
You can do ls -l for example.
We'll see.
What is that?
It's a long list.
It's going to show detailed information.
Or you can also give arguments with ls command, like you can give a path of a dir, for example,
/tmp dir
or a file path
But cp command definitely needs to pass arguments without passing arguments cp command will
not work.
So based on your commands and your need, you will use the right syntax.
Now, about the options there for one command, there could be many options and it's not possible to
memorize those things and you should not really.
Because there is always help available, for example, for cp, you can say cp --help
you can use this option, --help and it will show you.
First, the usage. how to use this, come on, show you three examples there for cp and you see there
a lot of option -a for archive -f for force.
-i for interactive.
If you want it to ask a question before overwriting any file, it will ask you a question, interactive.
And you see there -R, so you have Capitola R, small r ,recursive, so you can use any of these three to copy
directories recursively.
Mostly, you will see the syntax for the options hyphen one single hyphen if just as single alphabet,
but if there is a word, it will be hyphen, hyphen like hyphen, hyphen, recursive, or you can use
-r. Now every command will have its own options, SO run --help command and find out
your options that you want.
Or you can simply Google it.
That is also fine.
But help will be always at your fingertips, remember that you don't need to memorize these many things.
OK, resuming back our work.
So you have seen cp, command, let's see now mv command, mv is to move files, so mv and I would like
to move devopsfile4 or 3 to ops dir.
That's mv.
You can check ls ops.
If you want to move the director, you don't need to give any special option, I would like to move
ops dir, let's say, to dev dir.
OK, so it should have been moved now there is no ops here, it should be in the directory.
mv command is also used to rename file any file or dir, you can say mv, you can give a
source file, let's say a testfile1.txt will name it to testfile22.txt
OK, that's renaming.
A file or a dir, anyways, when we say file, it means any file in Linux.
OK, now little regular expression if you want to do multiple things at once, like if I want to copy
all the text file to a text dir. I will create a dir called textdir and I would like to move all the file that ends with
.text to textdir so I can use mv  * ,  star * means everything in Linux.
So when I say here * that means everything in the current dir.
But I'm going to say everything that ends with .txt, *.txt, move it to textdir.
You see that, that's gone.
Let's go to the textdir now.
rm command, rm is to remove files, so you say, rm, you can give a file name.
Let's say devopsfile10.txt, removes. Lets create some dir here.
Dir named mobile
Now, if you want to remove the directory, rm and the dir path, and it's going to throw you an error
Because to remove the directory, you have to use an option -r
Now this is -r option for rm command.
cp command also
have -r option
It removes a directory.
Gone, if you want to remove everything, let's create a few more things here.
I'm going to clear the screen now.
Created some directory, testdir
testdir, so I have five directories and some files, I want to clear everything I want to delete
everything. I can say rm -r and I can say *, which is a very dangerous command, by the way.
It's going to remove everything from your current working directly.
So be careful when you execute this command.
And sometimes people use f option also to force.
So it does not ask any question.
And you see everything is gone.
Now if you're not careful and if you're not in the right directory, let's say by mistake, you run
this command in your home directory.
And then it's going to remove everything from your home directory or imagine if you are in /etc dir
or some important other directory, server data and this command can delete everything and there is no
rolling back here.
There is no trash.
There is no recycle bin here.
If you want to get your files back now, then you have to do disk hard disk restoration, which could
be complicated and not 100 percent assurance that you'll get back all your files.
So be careful before you delete anything in Linux system.
So that's all in this video about this very, very basic commands, you can run your history command.
And see all the commands that you executed.
If you're done reviewing your work, if you're done practicing, then join me in the next video.