In this session, we will be seeing vim editor.
vim is a text editor.
We'll be editing, creating your text files throughout this course, and you should be very good with
this editor, if you're already good with any other text editor like Nano, you can continue with that.
But if you don't know any text editor in Linux, then we we're going to start with the vim editor by
default, vim editor will not be installed on CentOS Linux machine.
You will have vi Editor. vim is just an enhanced vim editor, so first, we will install the vim editor.
So let's go to our VM.
OK, so I am a vagrant user and this is a centos machine.
So to install you have to give the command sudo yum install vim -y.
We will be understanding this commands in detail later.
As of now, just run this command to install vim editor.
If for some reason your installation is not working, it's throwing you error, you don't need to troubleshoot
anything over here, recreate the VM, it's probably your VM is not getting Internet or you can bring
up Ubuntu VM that has vim by default installed.
And that's only if your installation is not working.
Don't waste your time and troubleshooting.
We are going to cover networking with vagrant later
So if you have any problem then you can troubleshoot.
As of now, just install. Not Working? Use Ubuntu VM.
OK, once you have installed your vim editor, let's create some file with it, so that's how you do.
There's nothing on here.
I'm in the home territory.
I'm going to run the command vim and a file name, So I will name it just simply firstfile.txt
Again, here extension is just for our reference.
It doesn't matter even and if you don't give extension, we can open this file and we're going to edit
this.
It's going to be a text file.
So give any name and hit enter.
You should see new file over here. When you open the vim editor first.
It will be in command mode.
There are three modes in vim editor.
You have command mode.
Then you have insert mode, in this mode, you're going to make changes and edit you want to do in the file
file, you have to get into insert mode by hitting I as in India.
Third mode is extended mode if you want to do some other operation like you want to save the file or
quit from the file, you can get into extended mode.
That will be by using colon : And we'll see how that works.
So currently, I'm in command mode, I'm going to hit I, as in India, and I get into insert mode and
I can then start writing here, so I'll just see you.
Welcome to Linux.
I know you're already welcomed, but again, I'm welcoming.
I hope you enjoy.
command line.
or just commands or whatever you want to write.
OK, I have written two lines in this file, and now I want to save it, so you have to hit escape to
go back to command mode.
And then hit colon : when you hit colon : you are in extended mode and in extended mode, you can
save the file.
You have to say  :w, which is write.
Save the file.
And we have written two lines, 45 characters.
Now, I didn't count that vim is counting, it told me.
OK, now you want to go out quite from this file again, you have to be in the command mode, so esc :q
esc + :q
Enter and it will quit, you can use your cat command to read the file.
OK, now we want to open this file once again, so vim and file name again or file path.
Now, this is not a new file
It's an existing file.
Now you want to make change again.
You can use I to insert or you can use o as in Oscar to get into insert mode. o is going to just
drop one level down.
And I'll add one more line, it is super important for you to practice Linux.
Before into devops, now that's the truth.
Even if you are a windows, there was.
I mean, if you're using Windows operating system for server and for automation, for everything, still,
you will need to have Linux skills because being DevOps you will still be using so many Linux based tools.
OK, now let's save this file and we're going to do all at once esc :wq, save and quit at the same time
esc :wq, save and quit at the same time
Hit Enter and you should see the file.
Now let's open it once again.
Simply want to quit, :q
quit out
Let's open it once again.
And this time, let's make some changes and, oh, that's a mistake and we don't want to save it, so
esc :q
:q , You're trying to do and it will not let you quit because you made some changes.
So again, esc + colon :
q!  that is forcefully quit without saving anything.
So whatever changes you made will not be saved and you go out.
All right, check that.
OK, that's very basic operations of vim editor, editing a file, making changes, what do
you want?
Saving, quitting, quitting forcefully.
So you have seen three modes when you open the file in command mode, insert mode to make changes
and you want to go to extended mode, you have to come to first command mode, escape and colon, and
then you get into extended mode.
Now, there are a lot of shortcuts in vim editor
You're going to see some of them very useful one
Like copy paste, cut, paste, redo, undo, stuff like that.
For this, we need a little bigger file, so I'm going to become the root user because in root users
home directory, there are two files.
These are long files.
OK, there's so much information in this file.
So this file is Anakonda-ks-cfg.
This file will have the information of the OS installation, what you selected while you're installing
operating system.
But we really did not install this operating system.
We did it through vagrant, but it will still have the information how it was installed.
OK, that's not the point.
Anyways, we just want to see some vim commands.
So let's open this file and I anaconda-ks.cfg.
OK, first thing I'll show you, setting up line numbers here, so colon :se nu, set numbers.
OK, there's an extended mode, it will show you the line numbers.
OK, now my cursor is on the line.
Number one, I want to go to the last line.
I can use a shortcut shift G.
Or capital G.
If you want to go to the first line two times small g, gg
One, shift g, last line, gg, first line.
Now sometimes you have hundreds and thousands of lines in a file using Down Arrow Up Arrow.
It's going to take some time, so shortcut.
OK, let's do some copy paste. Now before we see vim copy paste.
You know you can really select things in git bash right.
Click copy and you can take your cursor where you want and you can get into insert mode and pasted.
All right.
You can do that also.
But vim editor
How are we going to do?
Oh, let's see.
OK, I want to copy this line number 12.
So I take my cursor to line number 12 and I use a y two times, yy. This is yanking or copying, yy.
And then don't want to paste it somewhere, I'll go to the last line, shift g.
And I will hit p, p to paste.
OK, small p to paste below, if you want to paste above then capital P.
OK, that was neat.
Let's go again to line number one.
OK, if you want to copy multiple lines, so let's say I want to copy line number 16, 17, 18, 19.
OK, one, two, three, four, four lines.
So I take my cursor to number 16.
I hit 4yy.
OK, so 4 lines copied below my cursor, then let's paste somewhere.
Let's go to the end again and let's use p, small P to paste below.
You see four lines, pasted.
OK, feel free to copy and paste anywhere you want.
This really is not a configuration file.
You can do whatever you want in this file.
You can copy this file somewhere and you can do whatever operation you want.
OK, so that was copy paste.
Let's do now, cut paste.
And first line, so, cut, you can delete also. dd, d two times is to delete.
So if I hit dd. Deleted line number 1.
.
OK, and you can use u to undo, u as in umbrella.
If you want to delete multiple lines, again, like I want to delete this first five lines, I'll take
the cursor top, I say 5dd, deleted 5 lines and if you save, the lines are deleted, u to undo.
OK, similarly, you can do cut paste also, with dd you can cut.
So delete is actually going to cut, not just delete, so let's say I want to delete 23, 24, 25, 26
again, some four lines, 4dd
So I cut those four lines and go to the end and I will hit p to paste.
That's cut paste. yy and p is copy paste. dd and p is cut paste.
OK, so there are total 117 lines in this file, I'll show you one nice trick.
Let's go to the top.
So I want to delete all the lines in this file, so 117 dd, deleted everything.
If I save, everything is gone, but I can bring it back.
I can do u to undo.
OK, whatever changes I made, I'm not going to save it.  I'm going to say :q!
OK, so there are some shortcuts, gg, Capital, G, and if you want to move your cursor, you have wb.
nw, n represents the number like 5w, move the cursor, five words forward, like that. You have
u to undo, yy to copy.
nyy to copy multiple lines, p to paste below, capital P, to paste above and you have dd or ndd
One more thing, searching, searching some content in the file.
So let's open this file once again.
And if I want to search for something, let's say I want to search something as network.
So I use forward slash.
You have to be in the command mode, forward slash and use search for network, Hit Enter and it will show
you all the lines that have the word network.
And you can use, n, to go to the next search.
If you hit the search at the end, it will print their. Search hit bottom, continue at Top, n
2 lines I have network and it's case sensitive.
OK, so if you have capital N, it's not going to show you, that's Capital N
Linux is case sensitive and most of the things will be case sensitive from here onwards.
So that's all in this video about vim editor. I'll see you in the next one.