Software management or generally in Linux, we call them as packages.
So so far in your life, you must have installed or uninstall so many software on your Windows computer
or MacOS or your smartphones.
In the next, there are very different different methods of installing or setting up a package or software,
we're going to start with very basic one and then we're going to see different other methods of setting
up software.
So.
Log into your Linux VM and switch to root user.
And first, we are going to hit a command called tree. tree is a very interesting command, it shows directory
in a tree structure, like if you want to see the /var/log directory structure inside that subdirectories
and files, it will show it in a tree format, but it says command not found.
And no, don't try to use yum command here
We are going to see first a very manual way of setting up a package.
So open your browser.
And we'll search for the tree package on the Internet, download it and install it so you can just say
tree rpm
And hit enter.
And you should see various repositories like there is CentOS.pkgs.org and there is rpmfind
rpmseek, rpmpbone
So there are so many repositories on the Internet from where you can find and download the R.P.M.,
so I'll go with this R.P.M Find for now.
Let's click on it.
So it's pretty simple here, you can make a search and you should find the R.P.M. for tree, and there
are many rpm based operating system like you have fedora you have.
Maggie, you have open Susie, so R.P.M. packaging will be different for different different flavors.
We are looking for CentOS, so let's find CentOS , thers centos8, centos7
So since we have centos seven, we have this R.P.M..
I can click on it and it will download it in my local machine, but I want it to be downloaded in the
Linux machine.
So I'm going to right click
Copy link address and go to my shell and I'm going to use a command called as curl.
Which will be by default in your system, linux system, you say curl and paste the command
And you have to use -o
So curl will access this link, -o saying that output of this link should be saved to a file and
you can give a name to a file, will give the same name as the R.P.M. name.
And hit enter.
OK, if you do a ls now, you should find the R.P.M. in your current working directly where you executed
the curl command.
.
And to install it, we have the command R.P.M. -i I used to install, v for verbose, which means printing it
h is for  human readable, so print it in a human readable format when you're installing and you give
the path of the R.P.M..
And you will see that quickly got installed because really a very small package now you can have the
tree command.
tree /var/log
OK, you can see now the directress in a tree structure.
So that was just one example of installing an R.P.M. in a Red Hat Centos machine, and now maybe we're
excited and you want to install more software.
I am looking for a software package called httpd, which is a Web server package.
And will be seeing how it works, but right now we just worried about installing it, so we'll find
the right R.P.M. for cento seven that's there.
So I click copy, link, address.
I do the same thing.
I say wget, sorry, curl
And I paste the link, you can also use shift insert in gitbash to paste.
-o and copy the name of the file and just paste it. You select it, it will be copied,
you do a middle click and it will be pasted.
OK, you should have the R.P.M. now and now, let's try to install it, rpm -ivh httpd
It does not work, It says failed dependencies.
It's saying that you need to install these other RPM's.
And once you install this, then only you can install this as httpd rpm, so there is a dependency.
Now, there is just 4 dependency.
You can really find those download and install them, and then you can install httpd
What what if you have hundreds of dependencies?
Yeah, and that's the case so many times because in Linux principle, we understood we have small,
single purpose programs right now that are chained together to perform complex operations.
So you will very, very regularly hit this dependencies problem and that can be solved very easily.
Like we have rpm, which can install the package or you can even uninstall package.
You have other package managers also like yum for RedHat.
Before we go there, let's see some more option in R.P.M. rpm --help
Like you have -e to erase or you have -q to query. -a for all the files. Like query or verify all the
files.
So let's see some option.
rpm -qa
This will list all the rpms.
OK, maybe you're looking for some r.p.m. if you want to see whether it's installed or not.
Again, just a pipe grep like tree.
And if you want it, is that you can see rpm -e and then you can give the rpm name.
it will be gone.
Erased, now tree command
is not there.
Like that, there are many options with rpm. rpm -ivh  we have seen to install or capital U
to upgrade a package. e is to remove or erase
-ev --nodeps, so it's going to erase the installed package without checking its dependencies.
-qa to  to list all the RPM's.
-qi If you want more information, or qf, if you want to find out what package a file belongs to, so
you see some file and you want to see which package does this file belongs to.
OK, you can say rpm -qf, qc to list configuration of files for a package. That can
come handy when you're doing some troubleshooting with package management, but the better option for
managing your package is yum yum.
Let's see how that works.
So as we go on the Internet, search for R.P.M., download and install, instead of that, you can use
yum, which will do all that for you.
It will automate the process of package installation or management so that it does by using some configuration
file.
/etc/yum.repos.d, in this dir.
You should see some files, these files points to some repositories on the Internet, like, for example,
CentOS-base.repo
So it will have information of the repositories, so when you install any linux operating system, it will
always have access to some repositories. Like this is one repository information, mirrorlist, and that's
the url.
Like that all the files will have some repository information from where your yum can search for the
software, download and install and that also with dependencies.
OK, so like when I say yum search httpd, so I'm searching for a package named httpd in all those
repositories.
OK, so there are so many package that has a name like httpd-devel, which is for Devlopment httpd,
just like that, httpd manual, httpd tools and many, many other packages.
So if I want to install that, I'll simply say, yum, install a httpd.
So it turns out to be it's going to install a httpd plus its dependencies also, so it's saying
I'm installing this four dependencies and then this package.
So download and install with a dependency and I'm good with that.
I'll say y for.
Yes.
And that's it, it's installed.
If you happen to remove that, you can just see yum remove httpd
And I said, yes, remove that.
So now downloading and installing is very easy, Just yum install and the package name.
OK, now let's say I want to install a package, yum install jenkins.
And it says error, it has nothing to do because Jenkins package is not available in any of the repositories
that are available here.
So if it's not there, then you can always search for the Internet, you should find the vendor documentation
there, they'll mention the steps to install a particular package.
So let's take Jenkins' as an example.
And let's search for install Jenkins.
And I'm going do the official documentation, which is always preferred.
jenkins.io and it should have method of installing Jenkins in different, different environment.
You have Linux Mac OS, so let's click on Linux.
So scroll down, you have steps to install it on Debian machines, which we'll be doing later.
If you scroll down, see, you install Java.
method for fedora.
And or Red Hat/ CentOS, yes, we found that.
OK, so these are the commands.
So it's saying sudo wget. wget  is going to be working like curl, but first you need to have wget,
so let's install wget first and you can say that is a dependency for us.
yum install wget
So it is already installed.
So saying wget -o, output should be in this file.
And it's just accessing this link, a backward slash there means you can give it in, command in two lines
lines, so I just copy that.
So what this first command is doing, it is going to create.
This file with the repository detail.
It created the repository details over here.
OK, nice.
Now let's check the next command, rpm import.
So there is a key.
Sometimes you will have a key for a repository.
So you may have R.P.M. import command and a link.
So this key will provide us access to this repository.
And then yum upgrade it is saying, which is going to upgrade all the packages, which, if you want to skip.
Because that's going to take a very long time.
So it is Yum, install Jenkins and a Java.
Especially JDK.
Let's try that, so now Jenkins will be installed from this repository and then you have Java that will
be installed from our regular repositories and I'm going to say -y
-y so it does not ask me any question, yes or no, you see, there're like sixty 65 dependencies.
Which is installing Java and then it's installing Jenkins'.
Right.
So, you see, it's easy to do it with yum, but then yum should have access to the right repository
to download and install your software.
All right, so there is a command to directly create that file, sometimes you will see instruction
to open the file and put some content for the repository yum upgrade command.
You see, it's going to upgrade all the packages if you run a yum upgrade.
It's going to read all your packages and match it with the latest packages, and it will say there is
an update available so total 127 packages can be updated and one new package will be installed.
And this is going to take some time, but it is always preferred to update all your packages because
it may have security vulnerability or performance issue that can be fixed by this new patches.
And I'm going to say y.
And it's going to take some time.
OK, so yum search to search for a package, install to install a package, you have reinstall sometimes when
you're installing things, breaks, network go down and the package is not installed properly, you
can always reinstall. yum remove to remove a package yum update to update all the packages.
Or you can specify a package name, yum update and a package name.
You have group of softwares also like you have development group.
You can say, yum group list, it will show you group packages and then you can if you want to install
group packages, you can see a young group install and a group name which will install the group of
packages. yum  repolist to list all the enabled repositories that you have access to.
Sometimes you need to run this, command, yum clean all, which is going to clean clear the cache.
of your repository. yum history, to see the previous history of Yum. yum info packagename will
give you information about a particular package.