Welcome to this video.
In this video, we will be talking about services that are running in your Linux system or if you happen
to run your own service, how you can manage that.
So we have installed a package httpd, lets do it once again.
And it's already installed, httpd, is a Web service and the package name is httpd again,
so you say yum install httpd, it will install the package and you should have also a service named
httpd now, which can be managed by systemctl command. systemctl status httpd.
It will show you the status.
It says it's inactive.
Now, if you want to start the service, you can say systemctl start httpd.
And let's check its status again.
It should show active, so you see here some processes running, these are the process id.
Will get into what our processes and process IDs in the next video.
But really what it means to run a service means there are some processes running.
You want to start the process or you want to stop the process or you want to restart the processes.
You can use a systemctl command for a service.
So, like, start and stop, you also have an option of a restart.
If you make some changes, configuration change to your service, you can restart the service, so it
takes effect.
There's also one more option, instead of restart, you can try to reload or to reload the configuration
without even restarting the service.
So we started the service and it's running, but it's just running for now, if I reboot this machine
while booting up, this service will not come up.
I'll show that to you. Lets do exit.
And the exit, or I can just say reboot.
So if you want, you can do vagrant reload. exit out the vagrant reload or from the system, you can say
reboot and it should reboot your vm.
So before we reboot, you see the status was active, but after it comes up, let's see whether it's
running or not.
OK, it's up.
I have logged in.
Let me become the root user.
And now let's check the status, httpd and you see it's inactive, so it did not come at the boot time.
If you want to bring up a service at the boot time, then you have to say systemctl enable and the service
name like httpd
Now the service will come up at the boot time.
So it is only for the time if you really want to start the service, then you have to say.
systemctl start and the service name.
So far, have you been doing ssh to this machine through vagrant ssh and there is actually a service
called ssh, you can check its status if this always happens to be stopped.
We will not be able to do ssh. We will get into ssh in much more in detail in shell scripting.
OK, few other commands you want to check whether a service is running or not.
You can just run this command.
Also, systemctl is-active and the service name, it is inactive.
Because you see its status is stopped, you can say start, so we did enable, but we did not start the service.
Now, it started.
OK, so you can run systemctl status, but if you just want to check if t's active or not, you
can say is-active.
Like is-active, you also have is-enabled.
So it will tell you whether the services enabled for the boot time or not.
OK, so the way systemctl really works is based on its configuration file.
So for httpd, there should be a configuration file and this got created when you when we installed
htpd
OK, so the filepath is this system, the system slash multi-user.target.wants/httpd.service
So when we say systemctl  start httpd, it's going to read this file and we'll see execs start
how to start.
So this is actually the binary, which it is running with some options.
And some argument, so it really is going to run this command to start the service, to stop it's going
to run that command will understand what's a kill command later in processes.
So this configuration file got created automatically when we installed httpd through yum
But we'll see other way, when we just have a tar ball download and extracted, we don't have a
systemctl file to start the services, but we can create our own also that we're going to do later.
But that is all for now.
I will see you in the next video.