Hello and welcome in this video, we will be talking about archiving.
So there's so many times where you need to archive files and directories.
Especially when you want to take its back up or if you have a back up, you want to restore from that,
or if you have some files that's coming from the Internet or from somewhere else, it's an archive format.
You want to unarchive it.
So let's take an example, will go to /var/log dir and let's see if you want to archive all the
logs or let's see, we just want to archive the Jenkins logs.
Now there is a file jenkins', so mostly we do archiving of log files to move it to somewhere else so
we can clear the log files and save the disk space.
So I'm in a /var/log dir and I am going to archive the Jenkins' dir, so first we're going
to see with tar command
tar -czvf, c is to create, z is to compress, so archiving and then compressing it, v
is for  verbose and f is for file.
And I first give the archive name.
So I'm going to say jenkins_
I'll give some timestamp.
.tar.gz, which is the extension to represents a Tarball, gz represent, it was compressed
with z option, gunzip.
And then you give.
the path, which we really want to archive and compress, so that's Jenkins dir.
And you should see then.
Lets run ls -ltr, so it sorts properly, we see the Tarball there and this is called as tarball and we
can run a file, command and see, even if it does not have an extension, you can run file, command
and see what kind of file it is, Right?
It's gunzipped.
compressed data.
OK, let's see how we can unarchive it, so let's move it to /tmp/ dir and let's go to /tmp/ dir
So that's my tarball there, I want to extract it, so tar -x is for extract, c for will create,
x is for extract and the same options zvf
And if you give the path
And then you should see the Jenkins' dir there.
If you want to extract it somewhere else so you can use a -C, Capital C option and let's say
I want to extract /opt dir
So let's see /opt dir
You should see the jenkins dir there, extracted. So tar is legacy or old archiving command
of Linux, and it is still used. There are lot of options for it.
Its feature, Rich Tool.
So the top you should see some examples of tar command, you can see all the options you can compare to
tarballs by using -d
Or you can update an existing Tarbell.
You have more compression option you can use -a for auto compress, this -j for bzip2
-J for xz
These are other compression method like we used z for gunzip, you have bzip and you have xz.
Also for compression.
We have seen, -C to mention the dir, where we want to extract and many more.
Such interesting options really feature rich.
But much more simpler is really a zip command.
So let's do the same thing with zip command, zip command will not be available to you to install it.
So I'm going to say yum, install zip and unzip both.
And lets clear the screen, so same operation, I'm going to say zip -r, you have to give if you are
compressing a directory or  archiving directory. and I say httpd_06122020
12, 20, 20.
It's a back up, or it's a tarballs.
I would like to give a timestamp and then dot zip and then give the dir that you want to extract
Oh
Not this one.
I will extract the Jenkins' Jenkins underscore zero six one two, any dir that you would like
to archive.
Right.
Right, so that's our archive and same thing, let's move it to and this time let's move it to /opt dir.
OK, let's go to /opt dir.
Now, you have existing Jenkins dir over here, which it will try to overwrite
I'm going to remove that dirs and I'll say unzip Jenkins dot zip.
So unzip is just one zip
So you have two General method for archiving, tar and zip and will be using both, you know, of course,
when the need comes.
So that's all in archiving practice this command.
And I will see you then in the next video.