Instructor: Hello and welcome.
In this lecture, we will learn Ubuntu operating system.
Now most of the command
that we have learned previously works
on Ubuntu and CentOS both except few.
We will see the difference
and then you will find yourself
that's more or less same operating system
except some changes.
So let's bring up the Ubuntu OS.
So I have it in vagrant /f/vagrant-vms/ubuntu
is the vagrant file,
vagrant global -status.
Okay, so CentOS VM that is powered off
and Ubuntu VM, it is powered off.
This is same from VM setup lecture.
So you should be also having this.
All you can do is vagrant up.
The VM already is created
it's just going to power on the VM.
Okay, VM is up.
Let's log into it, vagrant ssh,
and let's clear the screen.
Let's check the OS, etc/os-release.
It's Ubuntu 22.
switch to the root user.
Let's check the logged in user.
it's root now pwd,
you're in root user's home directory.
So most of the command in Ubuntu
is same as CentOS except few.
Starting with the command useradd,
there is useradd command in Ubuntu,
if you run this, you say useradd
and let's say devops.
So it does add the user.
If you switch to that user,
you'll see some problems.
So there's no home directory, okay?
So it just took you to the root directory.
There is no home directory.
So when you use useradd command in Ubuntu
it will not create the home directory,
It will not create the mailing spool
and so many other things.
So I'm going to delete userdel -r devops.
see it says,
"There's no home directory found while deleting
and no mail spool found."
which you can specify,
you can use with -useradd option,
You have useradd command,
you have some options.
You can specify the home directory.
But the easy way in Ubuntu
is to use adduser command.
instead of useradd,
We have adduser in Ubuntu.
Let's do that, adduser
and it's also passwd included with that
So it is showing you that it has created a user devops,
created a group called as devops
and then adding devops user to devops group,
creating home directories
and moving files from /etc/skel.
So when you create user in Linux system
it'll copy all the files
from /etc/skel directory to users home directory.
And these are some files
we are going to see them in Bash scripting.
Next it is also asking the password
so we can enter the password also
and we'll ask some other information
like full name, room number,
work phone, blah blah blah.
Just keep hitting Enter
and if you're good with this
just say yes, Y for yes.
Okay, you should see the user devops
and rest everything the same,
passwd command, group add command,
usermod command, okay?
So that's one difference from CentOS to Ubuntu.
Adduser instead of useradd.
The other one is visudo command if you run,
we know it opens the sudos file in vi editor
but in Ubuntu the default editor is nano.
So if you hit Enter here
it'll open this file into nano editor.
If you know nano editor,
it's fine, you can use that.
But if you don't know,
you can just say Control + X to quit.
We want the default editor to be VIM.
So we can run this command,
export EDITOR=vim.
Now how this command works, export EDITOR=vim.
We are going to see that in Bash scripting.
These are variables
and this is setting variable temporarily
on your current shell.
If you logout and login,
you have to do it again.
But now if you run visudo,
it should open it in VIM editor.
There you go, okay?
And you can use colon Q to quit.
So that's the second difference.
Before running visudo,
you run export EDITOR=vim
if you want VIM editor.
But if you log out and log in,
then you have to do it once again
and we can make it permanent.
Also, again, we are gonna see that in Bash scripting.
Okay, the main difference is package manager.
So let's do the same thing.
What we really did in CentOS,
we'll download a tree package.
So in your browser,
just search for tree debian package for Ubuntu
and you should see ubuntu.package.org
or you can look for other sites as well.
And let's scroll down here
and you should see the mirror
and binary package URL.
So that's the URL.
You can just copy that
and you can say wget
or you can do curl also, paste that.
So it should download the debian package
and to install it dpkg -I tree.
Okay, now the tree command should be there, it's working.
To list all the debian package in your machine.
You can say dpkg -l.
And if you want to search something from there
you can say dpkg -l pipe grep
and the package name.
If you want to remove dpkg -r tree,
it's gonna remove the package.
That's manually downloading and installing it, right?
But as we have yum in Red Hat machine,
here we have apt.
So /etc/apt,
let's get into this directory
and you should see a file here sources.list.
This will contain the repository information, right?
So you have different URLs over here
and if you want you can add any new repository information.
But whenever you make change
or if you want to install any software
in Ubuntu or any Debian machine,
you run the command apt update first.
So it'll go and check all the repository
for the latest package and create a list.
You don't need to do that with Yum
because Yum will anyways.
Search first, create a list
and it can refresh the list every 24 hours.
But this is the place where Ubuntu or Debian
really beats Red Hat system
because of its software access.
It has tons and tons of softwares,
which is available from
so many repositories around the world.
So you an apt update, you update the list
and then you can see apt search tree
to search for a package named tree.
And you'll see so many packages
which has the name tree.
You can see apt install tree.
This also apt -get, which is older one.
You can just use apt and hit Enter.
So download and install and again with dependencies.
So tree does not have any dependencies
but if you want to install package like Apache 2
which is same as httpd,
in CentOS here we have Apache 2.
Well, that is having some dependencies.
It says these are the packages that will get installed
and it's also suggesting some other packages.
If you're good, you say Yes
and it'll download the package
with all the dependency and install them.
So Apache 2 is a service
and in Ubuntu,
if you install any service,
it'll start it automatically.
You'll see Apache 2 should be
already active and running,
Q to quit and it should be also enabled.
So if you see S is enabled,
it's also enabled.
So if you want to upgrade all the packages in Ubuntu,
you can say apt upgrade
and apt update is different,
apt update is just going to check the list
and update the list.
App upgrade will actually actually upgrade all the packages.
So this many package to be upgraded
I don't want to upgrade it now.
So I'm gonna say N,
you also have apt remove to remove the packages
like Apache 2 you want to remove.
There's also one nice option when you're removing it.
Let's install this package once again.
So we know apt remove is going to remove the package
but it'll not remove the configuration
and the data of those service or package.
If you want to remove cleanly,
like everything you can just say apt purge
and it'll remove the package
with all its configuration and all its data, okay?
A clean uninstall.
When you're installing
or uninstalling any such services in Ubuntu
like Apache 2 is a service.
It's a network service which will serve the webpages.
It is also going to update the firewall rules.
UFW is Ubuntu firewall.
So these are some differences that we have seen.
There are a few more different commands
which we'll be seeing in Bash scripting
and cloud computing AWS.
But that should be all for now.
So practice these commands
so you get hold of Ubuntu operating system also.
That's all in this video.
I will see you in the next one.